Ask most people which day of the week they dread the most and the answer is likely to be Monday.
问大多数人一周中最害怕哪一天，答案很可能是周一。
The first day of the week can make us grouchy and depressed, which is why the feeling is described as the Monday blues.
一周的第一天总会让我们变得烦躁又低落，这种情绪也因此被称为“周一忧郁症”。
But what is it exactly that makes us feel down and does it affect everyone?
但究竟是什么让我们心情变差，这种情绪又会影响每一个人吗？
Apparently, the most depressing day of the year is the third Monday in January, when it’s cold and dark outside.
显然，一年中最让人沮丧的日子是一月的第三个周一，彼时室外天寒地冻、昼短夜长。
This day was nicknamed ‘Blue Monday’ by psychologist Cliff Arnall in 2004.
心理学家克利夫·阿诺尔在2004年将这一天命名为“蓝色星期一”。
He came up with it after a holiday company asked him for a ‘scientific formula’ for the January blues.
当时一家度假公司请他推算出一个解释“一月忧郁症”的“科学公式”，这个说法便由此诞生。
Even if there was little science behind the formula, it’s probably true that the sound of our alarm clock on any Monday morning signals the dawning of a new week and possibly the end of our weekend of fun.
尽管这个公式并没有太多科学依据，但有一点或许是事实：每个周一清晨的闹钟声，都意味着新一周的开始，也可能宣告着充满乐趣的周末就此结束。
Research shows our Monday mood can be based on a direct comparison to the day before.
研究表明，我们周一的心情好坏，往往源于与前一天的直接对比。
It’s what psychologists call an emotional shift, and no other part of the week has a transition like it.
这就是心理学家所说的“情绪转变”，一周之中再也没有哪个时段会有如此强烈的状态切换。
Monday means the end of weekend lie-ins – it’s back to the routine and the realisation that there are five days ahead of the nine-to-five, and according to the BBC Bitesize website “If you can’t stand your job then the Monday blues can be very real.”
周一意味着周末懒觉的终结——大家要重新回归日常工作生活，同时意识到朝九晚五的日子还要持续五天。英国广播公司教学科普网站BBC Bitesize提到：“如果你无法忍受自己的工作，那么周一忧郁症就会真实地找上门来。”
And your miserable Monday is followed by trying Tuesday – the most popular day for sending out job applications.
在令人郁闷的周一过后，接踵而至的是“求职周二”——这一天是人们投递求职信的高峰期。
But is Monday as bad as we like to think it is?
但周一真的像我们想象中那么糟糕吗？
Feeling a bit low shouldn’t be confused with more serious depression, caused by other factors.
这种轻微的低落情绪，不应与由其他因素引发的更为严重的抑郁症混为一谈。
Writing for the BBC, author and presenter Claudia Hammond, argues that this low feeling might be a myth.
作家兼主持人克劳迪娅·哈蒙德在为BBC撰写的文章中指出，这种对周一的抵触感可能只是一种错误的固有印象。
She says: “There is a strong cultural idea that we don’t like Mondays.”
她表示：“不喜欢周一已经成了一种根深蒂固的文化观念。”
She mentions an Australian study in 2008 about how people reflected on their mood and found the day that scored the lowest was in fact Wednesdays.
她还提到2008年澳大利亚的一项研究，该研究调查了人们对自身情绪的回顾，结果发现情绪最低落的日子其实是周三。
So, when Monday comes, maybe we should give it a second chance!
所以，当周一来临时，或许我们应该再给它一次机会！